Guide to the Into the Woods
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Into the Woods
2014-2015
GEN MSS 1469
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.17
(1 box)
Ten photographs of trees in Columbia County, New York, created by Karen Halverson in 2014-2015. The photographer introduced tree flagging tape into the scenes with a range of colors.
Halverson, Karen, 1941-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Karen Halverson on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2016.
Arrangement
Arranged by the creator.
Karen Halverson (born 1941)
Karen Halverson is a documentary landscape photographer. Born in Syracuse, New York, Halverson received a Bachelor of Arts from Stanford University and Masters of Arts from Brandeis University and Columbia University. In 1975, she made her first photographic project, which documented the Garment District in New York City. Much of her work documents the tension between the natural and cultural landscapes of the American West. She is the author of Downstream: Encounters with the Colorado River (University of California Press, 2008), which retraces the route of John Wesley Powell's expeditions and explores what contemporary Americans have made of the waterway.
Description of Papers
Ten photographs of trees in Columbia County, New York, created by Karen Halverson in 2014-2015, and printed as color inkjet prints on Canson Platine Fibre Rag Paper, 20 x 24 inches (51 x 61 centimeters). In the photographs, she introduced tree flagging tape into the scenes with a range of colors. The prints are untitled with number sequences provided by Halverson to differentiate images. The collection comprises an edition numbered three of twelve.
In an artist's statement that accompanied the collection upon acquisition in 2016, Halverson describes the work:
It started with plastic tape I found attached to trees in South Carolina, strips of hot pink and blue punctuating the greens and browns of mighty oaks. Property markers, yes, but also adornment. Back home in New York State, I searched for colored tapes in the woods, but found very few. It was March, the landscape brown, the sky mostly gray. I craved color and the hardware store had it.
For the first time in many years of photographing landscape, I began introducing things into the field of view. I found that a single stroke of alien color would draw the eye into and around the photographic frame. I think of the tape or other material as a flourish, like a musical grace note, with the landscape retaining the upper hand. We humans have always made our marks on the land, one way or another. We claim territory, designate what's to be preserved or removed; we indicate the route, and we alter or add to what's there for the sake of visual pleasure. In these photographs, the introduced elements reference human intervention in the natural environment. But, of course, they are also a self-reference. I choose a location, experiment with my materials, and in time arrive at a photograph. Then, I gather my materials and leave things as they were. Would that all human interventions in the landscape were so benign.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Photography of trees -- New York (State) -- Columbia County -- Pictorial works; Trees -- New York (State) -- Columbia County -- Pictorial works; Columbia County (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; New York (State) -- Pictorial works; Inkjet prints; Photographs; Karen Halverson; Halverson, Karen, 1941-
- Into the Woods, 2014
  Scope and Contents
  Ten photographs of trees in Columbia County, New York, created by Karen Halverson in 2014-2015, and printed as color inkjet prints on Canson Platine Fibre Rag Paper, 20 x 24 inches (51 x 61 centimeters). In the photographs, she introduced flagging tape into the images with a range of colors. The prints are untitled with number sequences provided by Halverson to differentiate images. The collection comprises an edition numbered three of twelve.
  Arrangement
  Arranged by the creator.
  - Untitled, 4-29-14-68, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 10-15-14-2242, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Untitled, 1-23-15-2531, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Untitled, 4-28-14-1119, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Untitled, 4-22-14-18, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Untitled, 10-7-14-2047, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Untitled, 2-10-15-25658, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Untitled, 8-20-14-1593 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Untitled, 10-29-14-2272, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Untitled, 10-13-14-2113, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 10)